A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Dept. of Planning and Budget, 1987-2008
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Dept. of Planning and Budget, 1987-2008
The Library of Virginia
50065, 50066, 50067
7 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Toni Jamison, Virginia Dept. of Planning and Budget, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 East Broad Street, Richmond, Va 23219
Historical Information
Established by an Act of Assembly in 1976, the Dept. of Planning and Budget was created through the merging of the Division of the Budget and the Division of State Planning and Community Affairs. The duties of the Dept. of Planning and Budget include: the development and direction of an integrated policy analysis, planning and budgeting process within State government; the development, storage, retrieval and dissemination of data on the social, economic, physical and governmental aspects of the State; the formulation of an executive budget; conduct policy and program analysis for the Governor; the establishment of planning districts and standard metropolitan statistical areas; and the development and operation of a system of standardized reports of program and financial performance for management.
Past Directors of the Department of Planning and Budget include: Paul W. Timmreck (July 1984-January 1990), Karen F. Washabau (January 1990-January 1994), Robert W. Lauterberg (January 1994-January 1998), Scott D. Pattison (January 1998-June 2001), and Richard D. Brown (June 2001-August 2008).
Scope and Content
The Virginia Dept. of Planning and Budget collection contains correspondence, decision briefs and special projects materials spanning 1987 to 2008. Included are correspondence, decision briefs, special projects, memorandums and reports. These records document the activities of the Director of the Virginia Department of Planning and Budget.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Director's Correspondence and Subject Files, 1998-2008
II. Decision Briefs, 1987-1999
III. Project Documentation Files, 1998-2004
Contents List
- Series I. Director's Correspondence and Subject Files, 1998-2008 (Accession 50065)., Extent: 2 cubic feet of records. (Box 1-2.)
  The Director's Correspondence and Subject Files series (accession 50065) is housed in two (2) boxes and is arranged in chronlogical order. This series consists of decision briefs, letters (correspondence) and memorandums from Richard D. Brown (June 2001-August 2008), Scott D. Pattison (January 1998-June 2001) and Robert W. Lauterberg (January 1998).
  Decision Briefs document the Governor's Office response to requests from Executive Branch agencies for expenditure of funds from various sources controlled by the Governor's Office, approval of bond sales, letters from the Governor, and issuance of executive orders. Each Decision Brief usually includes: a description of the request including background material, discussion, and conclusions by the Policy Office; a recommendation from the Director of the Department of Planning and Budget; and concurrence from Secretary of Finance, the cabinet secretary overseeing requesting agency, and in some administrations the Director of Policy, Counselor to the Governor and Chief of Staff. If all concur, the Governor then signs the brief.
  - Robert W. Lauterberg, January 1998. (Box 1)
  - Scott Pattison, 1998. (Box 1)
  - Scott Pattison, 1999. (Box 1)
  - Scott Pattison, 2000. (Box 1)
  - Scott Pattison, January-June 2001. (Box 1)
  - Richard D. Brown, June 2001-December 2001. (Box 1)
  - Richard D. Brown, 2002-2003. (Box 2)
  - Richard D. Brown, 2004-2005. (Box 2)
  - Richard D. Brown, 2006. (Box 2)
  - Richard D. Brown, January-July 2007. (Box 2)
  - Richard D. Brown, July-December 2007. (Box 2)
  - Richard D. Brown, January-August 2008. (Box 2)
- Series II. Decision Briefs, 1987-1999 (Accession 50066)., Extent: 2 cubic feet of records. (Box 3-4.)
  The Decision Briefs series (accession 50066) is housed in two (2) boxes and is arranged in chronlogical order. This series consists of decision briefs signed by Paul W. Timmreck (1987-1990), Karen F. Washabau (January 1990-January 1994), Robert W. Lauterberg (January 1994-January 1998) and Scott D. Pattison (January 1998-December 1999). This series overlaps material in Series I.
  - 1987 (Box 3)
  - 1988 (Box 3)
  - 1989 (Box 3)
  - 1990 (Box 3)
  - 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1992 (Box 4)
  - 1993 (Box 4)
  - 1994 (Box 4)
  - 1995 (Box 4)
  - 1996 (Box 4)
  - 1997 (Box 4)
  - 1998 (Box 4)
  - 1999 (Box 4)
- Series III. Project Documentation Files, 1998-2004 (Accession 50067)., Extent: 3 cubic feet of records. (Box 5-7.)
  The Project Documentation Files series (accession 50067) is housed in three (3) boxes and is arranged in chronlogical order. The projects included in this series are: Virginia's Handbook on Planning and Performance (1998), Government Performance Project 2000: Virginia's Response and Surveys, and Impact of Tax Reform Plan and the 2004-2006 Budget on Localities.
  The majority of this series deals wtih the Impact of the Tax Reform Plan and the 2004-2006 Budget on Localities. It is housed in 2 boxes and is divided into two sections: alphabetical by locality and alphabetical by member. These records provide a comprehensive breakdown of the benefits of Governor Mark R. Warner's 2004 Tax Reform Plan by House and Senate District and locality. Features include: changes in the standard deductions, rates and brackets, filing threshold and age deduction. Other features included an increase in the sales tax and state cigarette tax, and a reduction in the sales tax on food. The Locality breakdown includes a profile of residents and income tax returns for each locality in 2001.
  - Virginia's Handbook on Planning and Performance, 1998. (Box 5)
  - Government Pefromance Project 2000: Virginia's Response and Survey, 1998-2000. (Box 5)
  - Impact of the Tax Reform Plan and the 2004 Budget on Localities, 2004. (Box 6)
  - Impact of the Tax Reform Plan and the 2004 Budget on Localities, 2004. (Box 7)